Guide to the Pee Wee Moore Papers, 1945-2009 RL.00908
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Pee Wee Moore papers
1945-2009
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Moore, Pee-Wee, 1928-
RL.00908
3 Linear Feet
"Pee Wee" (Numa Smith) Moore (born Raleigh, N.C., 5 March 1928; died Raleigh, N.C., 13 April 2009) was a professional jazz saxophonist, who performed and recorded with musicians including Louis Jordan, Illinois Jacquet, James Moody, Dizzy Gillespie, and Mary Lou Williams. The Pee Wee Moore Papers contain materials created and collected by Moore from throughout his career as a jazz saxophonist, including photographs, newspapaer clippings and other paper materials, as well as audio and moving image recordings of concerts, rehearsals, and oral history interviews.
500 Items
Access Restrictions
Collection is open for research.
Researchers must register and agree to copyright and privacy laws before using this collection.
In addition, original audiovisual materials are closed to patron use. Some use copies are available in the collection. Otherwise, Technical Services staff need to produce use copies before contents can be accessed.
All or portions of this collection may be housed off-site in Duke University's Library Service Center. The library may require up to 48 hours to retrieve these materials for research use.
Please contact Research Services staff before visiting the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library to use this collection.
Provenance
The Pee Wee Moore Papers were received by the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library as a gift in 2009.
Biographical Note
"Pee Wee" (Numa Smith) Moore was born in Raleigh, North Carolina on March 5, 1928. After attending Washington High School in Raleigh and Hampton College in Virginia, Moore began performing professionally as a baritone saxophonist in the early 1950s. He played with such artists as Lucky Millinder, Louis Jordan, Illinois Jacquet, James Moody, Dizzy Gillespie, Mary Lou Williams, Bill Doggett, and Rich Hargrove. While Moore resided in New York for much of his professional career, he eventually returned to Raleigh, where he performed regularly as a saxophonist throughout the 1980s and beyond. Moore passed away due to complications from pancreatic cancer on April 13, 2009.
Collection Overview
The Pee Wee Moore Papers contain materials created and collected by Moore from throughout his career as a jazz saxophonist. Materials are arranged into three categories: photographs, clippings and miscellaneous materials, and audio and moving image materials. Photographs include professional and candid pictures of Moore from throughout his life with images of jazz musicians including Dizzy Gillespie and James Moody. There are a large amount of clippings concerning Moore's life as a saxophonist, with a particular emphasis on his time performing with Louis Jordan, as well as manuscript drafts of jazz lead sheets. The collection also contains A/V materials including concert and rehearsal recordings from the 1980s along with oral history recordings related to Moore's life.
Jazz -- 1961-1970; Jazz -- 1971-1980; Jazz -- 1981-1990; Jazz -- 1991-2000; DVDs; Jazz; Phonograph records; Jazz -- 1941-1950; Jazz -- 1951-1960; Programs (documents); Photographs; Saxophonists; Clippings (information artifacts); Videocassettes; Raleigh (N.C.) -- Social life and customs -- 20th century; Saxophone music (Jazz); Jazz -- 2001-2010; Jazz -- Lead sheets; Jazz musicians; CD-ROMs; Audiocassettes; African American musicians; Moody, James, 1925-; Jordan, Louis, 1908-1975; Gillespie, Dizzy, 1917-1993; Moore, Pee-Wee, 1928-; Moore, Pee-Wee, 1928-
- Clippings, Programs, Sheet Music, and Miscellaneous Items, 1960-2009, 7 folders
  Scope and Contents note
  Clippings include newspaper articles about Moore's life and career as a jazz musician. One folder is devoted entirely to clippings related to Moore's time performing with Louis Jordan, and another folder contains photocopies of materials from a notebook of personal contacts compiled by Moore. This series also includes several programs from Moore's performances in the Raleigh, NC area during the 1990s along with programs from Moore's commencement ceremony at Wake Technical Institute and programs from Moore's funeral. One folder primarily contains manuscript drafts of jazz lead sheets presumably written by Moore along with a small amount of published music by other composers. Miscellaneous items include Moore's certificates from Wake Technical Institute, documents concerning the repairs of Moore's home in Raleigh, NC, a calendar featuring Moore on the cover, and the plaque from Moore's funeral.
  - Clippings, programs, sheet music, and miscellaneous items (Box 1)
- Photographs, 1945-2008, 7 folders
  Six folders arranged by size and original order when possible. Pictures include a range of candid shots from Moore's travels and his time living in New York and North Carolina. There are also pictures of Moore's performances, including many with local jazz musicians from the Raleigh-Durham area. There are several images with notable figures such as Dizzy Gillespie, James Moody, and President Ronald Reagan. One folder contains negatives that correspond to many of the photographs in the collection.
  - Photographs (Box 1)
    Scope and Contents
    Clippings folders; Photographs folders 1-3
  - Photographs (Box 1A)
    Photograph folders 4-6 and negative folder
- Audio and Moving Image Materials, 1957-2009, 1 box
  Contains a variety of audio and moving image recordings of various concerts and rehearsals Moore was a part of in the 1980s and 1990s, along with three of the commercial recordings he performed on during his career, including two with Dizzy Gillespie. Also contains two sets of oral history interviews conducted with Moore in the 2000s.
  - Audio Cassettes
    - 101: August 19, 1984 art school (Box 2)
    - 102: Ed Massey and Pee Wee (Box 2)
    - 103: Elmer and Pee Wee (Box 2)
    - 104: Pee Wee, Sistie, Ed, Elmer at Irregardless, Spring 1996 (Box 2)
    - 105: Pee Wee Moore Concert 6/12/93 Raleigh Mem Aud (Box 2)
    - 106: EM17 X (Box 2)
    - 107: Wake Med Cafe 9/29/04; Pee Wee and Chris (Box 2)
  - Compact Discs
    - 108: Interview with Pee Wee Moore by Marshall Wyatt (Box 2)
    - 109: Interview with Pee Wee Moore by Elmer Gibson (Box 2)
    - 110: Dizzy Gillespie at Newport, 1957 (Box 2)
  - LPs
    - 201: Pee Wee Moore Quartet, Saxey, 1980 (Box 2)
    - 202: Dizzy Gillespie Octet, The Greatest Trumpet of Them All (Box 2)
  - Moving Image Materials
    Contains VHS and DVD recordings of two concerts featuring Moore as well as a tribute DVD to Moore's life.
    - VHS and DVD recordings (Box 2)